So, I went from, you know, a talented
and gifted student with straight A's to
failing like literally every subject the
first quarter of seventh grade. So, I
was chronically truant. I think I was
averaging 19 days a quarter that I was
actually showing up for school.
My mother didn't know because the school
never notified her and by the time she
got home from work at 6:00 p.m., we were
all sitting around like pretending to do
our homework.
So, my poor mother had no idea until
about midway through the eighth grade. I
was so chronically truant that I was
failing all of my major subjects.
So,
meanwhile, while I'm skipping school,
I'm hanging out with the wrong people.
Much older crowd.
Friends of my older brother and older,
you know, just an older crowd and just
getting in trouble and
I fall in love with a much older
boyfriend at the time.
Think I'm in love and we want to get
married and run away and get married.
And so, by the time I was in the ninth
grade, I'm 14 years old, found myself
pregnant.
My boyfriend at the time had give me a
diamond ring. We were engaged. We're
going to get married. So, we run away.
He was
26 at the time. I was 14. My mother,
when she finds out, was going to have
him arrested. Like she she was going to
put him in jail.
So, I run away from home and think,
well, we've got this. We're going to get
married and we're going to have the baby
and everything's going to be great.
The mind of a 14-year-old.
Obviously, things didn't work out that
way. So, interestingly, I went to my
father, who had been out of the picture
most of my life, and asked for him to
sign for me to get married because I had
to because of my age, one of my parents
had to legally sign over my legal
guardianship to my husband. So,
they literally signed over my legal
guardianship to my husband.
So, my dad,
thinking he would have one less child to
pay child support for cuz once he signed
over my guardianship, he
>> For him, cuts the child support bill.
>> Paid $100 less a month in child support.
So, he signed over my legal guardianship
to my husband. We get married the day
after my 15th birthday. I was 8 months
pregnant
at the time. So,
I guess fast forward a little bit. A
year and a half later, I was back at
home. My mother was taking me to GED
classes at night. I was sneaking to go
to GED classes when I was still married.
My husband didn't approve of me going to
school.
So, once we separated, my mom made sure
I stayed in school, got my GED. She
would bring her typewriter home from
work and she taught me how to type on
the kitchen table. So, she taught me how
to type and take a little shorthand and
I went and got a job as a secretary. I
lied about my age. I went and got a job
as a secretary
when I was 16.
So, started working as a secretary and
then worked as a waitress in the evening
in a bar. Also lied about my age to work
in a bar. That was the only option up in
the area where I was working. So, for
the next
several years, I worked two jobs as a
secretary and a waitress.
You know, my motivation
really was my son.
>> Mhm.
>> It was
kind of a significant moment for me and
I've had a few in my life.
When my son was born, I had never baby
sat before. I'd never held a baby. I
didn't know anything about babies or
children. And when he was born, he was
such a good baby. His crib was at the
end of my bed in my bedroom. And I'd
wake up in the morning and he'd be awake
and he'd just be looking at me waiting
for me to wake up, right? Not crying,
not nothing. He'd just be looking at me.
And so,
>> That is remarkable.
>> Yeah. About 3 weeks into this
experiment, I'm looking at him one
morning and it just dawns on me like
for the first time that I'm a parent.
And that
that helpless little baby was completely
relying on me. And
my mother was
always stressed the importance of
education and work to us. And here I
was, you know, my husband didn't allow
me go to school. I would never be able
to get a job. And I'm looking at this
poor little innocent baby and I'm
thinking his whole life depends on me
and
what am I going to be able to provide
with a ninth grade education? Not much.
So, that was a aha moment.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I'm going to resist the
temptation to ask 300 questions about
the last few minutes that you shared
because we'll we'll end up spending all
of our time there if I do that, but I am
curious for you. I'm trying to put
myself
in your shoes at that young age.
When you and we we don't need to get
into the details unless you'd like to
share, but
when you separated from your then
husband, like when that happened, what
did you think
was going to become of you? Like what
did you envision
your path would be at that point? I have
to imagine that it would have just been
incredibly challenging. I don't know.
You can't believe everything you read on
the internet, but I read that when you
were a young girl you dreamed of being a
lawyer. I don't know if that's true or
not.
>> Mhm.
>> And then flash forward, you go through
this entire tumultuous experience
and you land back at home. Where did you
think your life was
headed? Where did you think you were
headed at that point?
>> Well,
I knew that with a ninth grade education
and a single mom that I had zero chance
of being able to do what I
thought was most important in the world
and that's take care of my son. And
when I first moved back home, I got my
GED, but I still was not able to easily
find a job at my age. I was, you know,
16, almost 17. I had to wait till I was
16 and 9 months to take the test to get
the GED.
Interestingly, you needed 255 to pass
the test. I got 256. Well, I passed it
by one point.
>> Oh my god.
>> Just another little like footnote of my
life.
>> Talk about the sliding door moments.
Holy cow, right?
>> So, my mother had always stressed the
importance of education and work. So, I
knew I had to go back to school and I
wanted to go to college. I didn't want
my son to be subject to the same crappy
neighborhoods and the same crappy
schools that I went to. I wanted him to
have a real chance and I knew if I was
going to do that, I had to go back to
school and get a college education. If I
didn't do that, he would be doing I was
standing in the same food stamp line my
mother stood in with me. I remember the
first day I went to get food stamps,
going to the big white building by
Prince George's Plaza right near my home
and standing in the same line with my
son that I stood in with my mom when I
was a kid and I was like, "This is not
my path. This can't be my path."
And when I got my job as a secretary,
they offered tuition reimbursement to go
to college. So, I started at community
college. I just started taking one class
a semester.
And that's where it started, one class a
semester and they reimbursed me for it.
So.
>> So,
I recall, I mean, for people who don't
have context,
we've been we've been trying to schedule
this for a while and understandably you
got a lot of balls to juggle and
I remember hearing just pieces of your
story. This was God, it has to be what,
more than a year ago now, I'm sure. Time
flies, but it's been a it's been a long
while and I used to remember thinking to
myself,
"God, I hope someday that we can have
this conversation on the podcast." So, I
want to thank you again for doing it.
How do you then go from there? What is
the connective tissue sort of the
catalyzing events that ultimately get
you into law enforcement, right? What is
what are the first
few dominoes that get tipped over that
start to push you in that direction?
>> So, to be fair, my family's a public
service family. My father was
firefighter, my oldest brother had
become a firefighter right out of high
school. My other brother was a police
officer. I was working as a secretary. I
was taking that one class a semester,
working as a secretary, trying to get my
son in private school. I wanted him in
private school. I did not want him going
to those schools. I was still living in
the same crappy neighborhood. But, I
wanted my son in a good school. And I
saw an ad. I was 23 years old. I saw an
ad in the Washington Post for the
Metropolitan Police Department. They
were hiring.
And what caught my attention, it's a
full-page ad in the Post. The half of
the page was said tuition reimbursement.
I'm like, "Oh my god, tuition
reimbursement. I'm paying for one class
a semester. It's going to take me 30
years to get a degree."
>> Mhm.
>> So, I went with a friend, and we went
and stood in line. They were hiring a
thousand cops. This was during the crack
cocaine wars in Washington, early 1990.
So, 500 murders a year. D.C. was known
as the murder capital of the world at
the time.
So, I just went and stood in line with a
thousand other people, went and took the
test, and
I came out I want to say I came out like
60 out of a thousand people on that
test. So, they called me right away. I
was the only white female in the room,
right? This is back in the early '90s.
Washington, D.C. was about 89%
African-American, right? So, I felt the
same drive my mother felt
taking care of us is that I have a son
that needs me. He needs me to provide
for him, and the only way I'm going to
do this is get a good job. Government
job, not a bad option, and go back to
school and get my degree. So, I got
hired by the Metropolitan Police in
1990, started walking a foot beat. My
first day out of the academy was the
Mount Pleasant riots. So, my first day
out of the academy, I went to work and
didn't come home for 5 days. It was
great.